{"Corporate Law":[
  {
   "id": "1",
   "question": "The Governing Board of the Corporate Affairs Commission (“CAC”) comprises how many members?",
   "options": {
    "a": "10",
    "b": "12",
    "c": "13",
    "d": "15"
   },
   "answer": "12",
   "reason": "The governing board of CAC comprises 12 members. See Section 2 of CAMA 2020."
  },
  {
   "id": "2",
   "question": "The quorum for the meeting of the Board of the Corporate Affairs Commission is?",
   "options": {
    "a": "4",
    "b": "5",
    "c": "6",
    "d": "7"
   },
   "answer": "5",
   "reason": "The quorum for the meeting of the governing board of CAC is 5. See Section 6(3) CAMA 2020."
  },
  {
   "id": "3",
   "question": "The following are the types of business organizations recognised by the Companies and Allied Matters Act except",
   "options": {
    "a": "Company Limited by Guarantee",
    "b": "Sole Proprietorship",
    "c": "Incorporated Trustees",
    "d": "Partnership"
   },
   "answer": "Incorporated Trustees",
   "reason": "While the concept of incorporated Trustees are recognised by CAMA 2020, you should note that a key feature of Incorporated Trustees is that they are not allowed to engage in business. This is a key difference between it and company limited by guarantee as the later is allowed to do business but cannot distribute the profit to members"
  },
  {
   "id": "4",
   "question": "The form for application for registration of the company is:",
   "options": {
    "a": "Form CAC 1",
    "b": "Form CAC 1.1",
    "c": "Form CAC 1A",
    "d": "Form CAC 2.1"
   },
   "answer": "Form CAC 1.1",
   "reason": "The form used for the registration of a company is Form CAC 1.1 headed “Application to Register a Company”."
  },
  {
   "id": "5",
   "question": "The Attorney General is required to grant approval within how many days where there are no objections for a company limited by guarantee",
   "options": {
    "a": "30 days",
    "b": "One month",
    "c": "21 days",
    "d": "28 days"
   },
   "answer": "30 days",
   "reason": "The Attorney General of the Federation shall, within 30 days, grant authority to register a company limited by guarantee where there are no objections or any other cogent reason to refuse the grant. See Section 26(5) of CAMA."
  },
  {
   "id": "6",
   "question": "The minimum number of trustees that may apply for registration under Part F of CAMA is:",
   "options": {
    "a": "4",
    "b": "2",
    "c": "1",
    "d": "5"
   },
   "answer": "2",
   "reason": "The minimum number of trustees that can be registered under part F is 2. See Section 823(1) of CAMA."
  },
  {
   "id": "7",
   "question": "The CAC form to fill when filing the annual returns of a business name is:",
   "options": {
    "a": "CAC 6",
    "b": "CAC/BN/6",
    "c": "CAC/BN/7",
    "d": "CAC 7"
   },
   "answer": "CAC/BN/6",
   "reason": "CAC/BN/6 is headed “Annual Return of Business Names"
  },
  {
   "id": "8",
   "question": "Who can bring an application for the dissolution of Heroes for Nigeria (An Incorporated Trustee)?",
   "options": {
    "a": "The governing Body or Council",
    "b": "One or more Trustees",
    "c": "Members of the association constituting not less than 50% of the total membership",
    "d": "All of the above"
   },
   "answer": "All of the above",
   "reason": "Section 850 of CAMA."
  },
  {
   "id": "9",
   "question": "The Stamp Duty payable on the Memorandum and Articles of Association of a company is?",
   "options": {
    "a": " Ad valorem",
    "b": "Fixed",
    "c": "40%",
    "d": "No stamp duties is paid"
   },
   "answer": "Fixed",
   "reason": "The stamp duty payable on the MEMOART is fixed, while that of the statement of minimum share capital (now CAC 1.1) is ad valorem."
  },
  {
   "id": "10",
   "question": "Which of the following is not required to have a special clause?",
   "options": {
    "a": "Company limited by shares",
    "b": "Company limited by guarantee",
    "c": "Incorporated Trustee",
    "d": "None of the above"
   },
   "answer": "Company limited by shares",
   "reason": "A company limited by guarantee and an Incorporated Trustee are required to have a special clause in their MEMART/Constitution respectively. The special clause is to the effect that the income and property of the company or association will be applied solely towards the object, and no part of it shall be distributable to members, even if the company or association winds up."
  },
  {
   "id": "11",
   "question": "There can be more than one promoter to a company",
   "options": {
    "a": "True",
    "b": "False",
    "c": "The minimum is 2",
    "d": "The maximum is 2"
   },
   "answer": "True",
   "reason": "All subscribers to a memorandum are regarded as promoters. The law does not provide for any minimum nor maximum. see section 85 CAMA 2020"
  },
  {
   "id": "12",
   "question": "One of the following upheld the CAMA provision that a pre incorporation contract may be ratified by the company upon incorporation.",
   "options": {
    "a": "Kelner v Baxter",
    "b": "Societe Generale Bank v Societe Generale Favouriser",
    "c": "Leopold Borrne v Sensolid",
    "d": "Societe Generale Bank v Sem Edowire"
   },
   "answer": "Societe Generale Bank v Societe Generale Favouriser",
   "reason": "Kelner v. Baxter is the authority on the common law principle that pre-incorporation contract are not valid. section 96(2) CAMA 2020 changes this provison and Societe Generale Bank is the new position on this"
  },
  {
   "id": "13",
   "question": "The saying `an exempted company has the status of unregistered company` means none but one of the following:",
   "options": {
    "a": "An exempted company is exempted from payment of company taxes",
    "b": "An exempted company is exempted from filing annual reports",
    "c": "An exempted company cannot sue or be sued in Nigeria",
    "d": "An exempted company is exempted from holding General meetings"
   },
   "answer": "An exempted company is exempted from payment of company taxes",
   "reason": "When we say an exempted company has the status of an unregistered company, it means that, among others, the company is exempted from the payment of taxes in Nigeria."
  },
  {
   "id": "14",
   "question": "An incentive that allows you get back import duties paid is:",
   "options": {
    "a": "Duty draw back",
    "b": "Duty repatriation",
    "c": "Pioneer status",
    "d": "Duty reservation"
   },
   "answer": "Duty draw back",
   "reason": "Duty drawback scheme is the tax incentive that allows importers of materials used in the manufacture of exported goods may claim repayment of import duties earlier paid in respect of the materials. The application for duty drawback must be made within a maximum of two years from the date of exportation."
  },
  {
   "id": "15",
   "question": "The maximum accumulated tax holiday available to an industry with pioneer status in Nigeria is:",
   "options": {
    "a": "5 years",
    "b": "3 years",
    "c": "7 years",
    "d": "4 years"
   },
   "answer": "5 years",
   "reason": "Pioner Status grants one tax holiday for three years with a further possible extension for 2 extra years thus making it 5 years in total"
  },
  {
   "id": "16",
   "question": "CERPAC means:",
   "options": {
    "a": "Combined Expatriate Registration Permit Authorised Card",
    "b": "Combined Expatriate Residence Permit and Aliens Credit",
    "c": "Combined Expatriate Residence Permit and Allowance Card.",
    "d": "Combined Expatriate Residence Permit and Aliens Card."
   },
   "answer": "Combined Expatriate Residence Permit and Aliens Card.",
   "reason": "CERPAC stands for Combined Expatriate Residence Permit and Aliens Card. The card is also referred to as green card."
  },
  {
   "id": "17",
   "question": "The procedure for change of name is contained in what section of CAMA?",
   "options": {
    "a": "Section 30",
    "b": "Section 31",
    "c": "Section 29",
    "d": "Section 32"
   },
   "answer": "Section 30",
   "reason": "The procedure for a change of a company name is contained in Section 30 of CAMA 2020."
  },
  {
   "id": "18",
   "question": "The theory of good corporate governance which posits that the company has more than the interest of its owners and employees at stake, but also that of the General public is:",
   "options": {
    "a": "The German Model Theory",
    "b": "The Agency Theory",
    "c": "The Stewardship Theory",
    "d": "The Stakeholder Theory"
   },
   "answer": "The Stakeholder Theory",
   "reason": "The stakeholder theory of corporate governance considers the public interest among other things because it views the public as necessary stakeholder in corporate actions."
  },
  {
   "id": "19",
   "question": "The decision of the Board of Directors is usually",
   "options": {
    "a": "Unanimous resolution",
    "b": "Special resolution",
    "c": "Ordinary resolution",
    "d": "General resolution"
   },
   "answer": "Unanimous resolution",
   "reason": "The decision of the board of directors is taken to be a unanimous resolution."
  },
  {
   "id": "20",
   "question": "Failure to file annual returns for a consecutive period of __________ is a ground for striking the name of a company off the companies register:",
   "options": {
    "a": "10 years",
    "b": "7 years",
    "c": "8 years",
    "d": "12 years"
   },
   "answer": "10 years",
   "reason": "Failure to file annual returns for a consecutive period of 10 years is a ground for striking the name of a company off the companies register. See Section 425 (3) of CAMA."
  },
  {
   "id": "21",
   "question": "The Chairman of the Board of CAC is appointed by _________ on the recommendation of ____________",
   "options": {
    "a": "Minister of Trade, Attorney General of the Federation",
    "b": "Minister of Finance, President",
    "c": "President, Minister of Trade",
    "d": "President, Attorney General of the Federation"
   },
   "answer": "President, Minister of Trade",
   "reason": "The chairman of the governing board of CAC is appointed by the President of Nigeria on the recommendation of the Minister of Trade. See Section 2(2)(a) of CAMA 2020."
  },
    {
   "id": "22",
   "question": "Members of the Board of CAC are appointed to hold office for ____",
   "options": {
    "a": "2 years",
    "b": "3 years",
    "c": "4 years",
    "d": "5 years"
   },
   "answer": "3 years",
   "reason": "The members of the governing board of CAC are appointed to hold office for a term of three years but may be re-appointed. See Section 3(1) of CAMA."
  },
    {
   "id": "23",
   "question": "The Companies and Allied Matters Act is divided into how many parts?",
   "options": {
    "a": "7",
    "b": "6",
    "c": "3",
    "d": "5"
   },
   "answer": "7",
   "reason": "CAMA 2020 has 7 parts: Parts A-G"
  },
    {
   "id": "24",
   "question": "As a general rule, the minimum and maximum age limit for appointment as a director in a private company is?",
   "options": {
    "a": "21 years and 70 years respectively",
    "b": "18 years and 70 years respectively",
    "c": "18 years and 75 years respectively",
    "d": "18 years and none respectively"
   },
   "answer": "18 years and none respectively",
   "reason": "For a private company, there is no restriction on the maximum age limit of directors. For a public company, if a person above 70 years is to be appointed a director, special notice disclosing his age must be given to the company. See Section 278(1) and 282 of CAMA. In both private and public companies, directors must be at least 18 years. See Section 283 of CAMA."
  },
    {
   "id": "25",
   "question": "A chamber of commerce is registered under what part of CAMA",
   "options": {
    "a": "Part A",
    "b": "Part B",
    "c": "Part C",
    "d": "Part D"
   },
   "answer": "Part B",
   "reason": "section 852 provides that only a company limited by guarantee can take the name Chamber of Commerce and a company limited by guarantee is under part B of CAMA 2020"
  },
    {
   "id": "26",
   "question": "A company limited by guarantee lacks one of the following?",
   "options": {
    "a": "Directors",
    "b": "Company Secretary",
    "c": "Shareholding",
    "d": "Memorandum of Association"
   },
   "answer": "Shareholding",
   "reason": "A Company Limited by Guarantee does not have a share capital. See Section 26(2) of CAMA."
  },
    {
   "id": "27",
   "question": "What section provides for the alteration of the object clause?",
   "options": {
    "a": "Section 30",
    "b": "Section 127",
    "c": "Section 51",
    "d": "Section 80"
   },
   "answer": "Section 51",
   "reason": "Section 50(2) CAMA states that the alteration of the object clause must be in accordance with section 51 of CAMA 2020"
  },
    {
   "id": "28",
   "question": "Which of the following alterations must be confirmed by court?",
   "options": {
    "a": "Name Clause",
    "b": "Object Clause",
    "c": "Increase of share capital",
    "d": "Reduction of share capital"
   },
   "answer": "Reduction of share capital",
   "reason": "Section 130 of CAMA provides that the articles must empower a company before it can reduce its share capital and such reduction must be approved by court."
  },
    {
   "id": "29",
   "question": "The following except one can requsition an Extra Ordinary General meeting?",
   "options": {
    "a": "Board of Directors",
    "b": "Members",
    "c": "Company secretary",
    "d": "Resigning Auditor"
   },
   "answer": "Company secretary",
   "reason": "Section 413 allows for a resigning Auditor to requisition an EGM"
  },
    {
   "id": "30",
   "question": "Which of the following circumstance is the right to demand poll non-existent",
   "options": {
    "a": "Adjourment of Meeting",
    "b": "Election of Chairman",
    "c": "Election of Audit committe",
    "d": "Appointment of directors"
   },
   "answer": "Election of Audit committe",
   "reason": "For Adjourment and Election of chairman, the Articles must expressly take away such right but for Election of Audit committe, it irrelevant if such provision is in the articles or not, the right to demand poll will not exist in such cases."
  },
    {
   "id": "31",
   "question": "One of the following content is only necessary for Public companies in Annual records?",
   "options": {
    "a": "Directors report",
    "b": "Auditors report",
    "c": "Statement of accounting policy",
    "d": "Balance sheet"
   },
   "answer": "Statement of accounting policy",
   "reason": "See section 377 CAMA 2020"
  },
    {
   "id": "32",
   "question": "What section of the Nigerian Investment Promotion Commission Act assures investors of a dispute resolution process?",
   "options": {
    "a": "section 18",
    "b": "section 20",
    "c": "section 25",
    "d": "section 26"
   },
   "answer": "section 26",
   "reason": "Section 26 NIPC Act assures investors of a dispute resolution process"
  },
    {
   "id": "33",
   "question": "If there exist 60 directors, the quorum for BOD will be what?",
   "options": {
    "a": "30",
    "b": "20",
    "c": "25",
    "d": "15"
   },
   "answer": "20",
   "reason": "Section 290 CAMA provides that the quorum can either be 25 or 1/3 depending on which is less. In this case, 1/3 of 60 is 20 which is less than 25."
  },
    {
   "id": "34",
   "question": "Can a private company invite the public to subscribe to its securities?",
   "options": {
    "a": "NO",
    "b": "Yes",
    "c": "Maybe",
    "d": "None of the above"
   },
   "answer": "Yes",
   "reason": "section 67 of ISA has been amended by section 43 of BFA allowing for a private company to invite the public"
  },
    {
   "id": "35",
   "question": "The form for registering of securities is called what?",
   "options": {
    "a": "CAC 6",
    "b": "CAC 10",
    "c": "SEC 6",
    "d": "SEC 10"
   },
   "answer": "SEC 6",
   "reason": "see section 279(2) ISA"
  },
    {
   "id": "36",
   "question": "What is the principal Law on Mergers",
   "options": {
    "a": "Investment and Securities Act",
    "b": "Federal Competition and Consumers Protection Act",
    "c": "National Office for Technology Acquisition and Promotion Act",
    "d": "Securities and Exchange Commission Rules"
   },
   "answer": "Federal Competition and Consumers Protection Act",
   "reason": "Section 168 of FCCPA has repealed sections 118 - 128 of ISA"
  },
    {
   "id": "37",
   "question": "The following are forms of a prospectus except?",
   "options": {
    "a": "Abridged prospectus",
    "b": "Deemed Prospectus",
    "c": "Statement in Lieu of prospectus",
    "d": "None of the above"
   },
   "answer": "None of the above",
   "reason": "The forms of prospectus includes: full prospectus; Abridged prospectus; Deemed Prospectus; Statement in Lieu of prospectus"
  },
    {
   "id": "38",
   "question": "Where share qualification is required, a director who is not qualified must obtain his share qualification within _____after his appointment",
   "options": {
    "a": "21 days",
    "b": "One month",
    "c": "Three months",
    "d": "Two months"
   },
   "answer": "Two months",
   "reason": "Where share qualification is required, a director who is not qualified must obtain his qualification within two months after his appointment. See Section 277(2) of CAMA."
  },
    {
   "id": "39",
   "question": "Failure to hold statutory meeting could be a ground for",
   "options": {
    "a": "Automatic winding up",
    "b": "Members voluntary winding up",
    "c": "Creditors voluntary winding up",
    "d": "Compulsory winding up"
   },
   "answer": "Compulsory winding up",
   "reason": "Failure to hold a statutory meeting could be a ground for compulsory winding up of the company. See Section 571 (b) of CAMA."
  },
    {
   "id": "40",
   "question": "The period for filing the annual returns for business name is",
   "options": {
    "a": "Between January 1 and June 30 each year",
    "b": "Between January 1 and July 30 each year",
    "c": "Between June 30 and December 31 each year",
    "d": "Between July 30 and December 31 each year"
   },
   "answer": "Between January 1 and June 30 each year",
   "reason": "The annual returns of a business name must be filed not later than June 30, every year. See Section 822(1) of CAMA."
  }
]
 }
